<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Le Bras Lab @ WHOI</title>
    <link>https://ilebras.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ilebras.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Le Bras Lab @ WHOI</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ilebras.github.io/images/icon_hu7732e1026a0bb9a199bd2a822c780345_104731_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Le Bras Lab @ WHOI</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Western Irminger Sea Ventilation</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2022-irm-ventilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2022-irm-ventilation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the subpolar North Atlantic, globally significant quantities of carbon dioxide and oxygen enter the water column via dense water formation. In order for these carbon- and oxygen-rich waters to ventilate the deep ocean and affect global climate, however, they must be transported away from their formation sites. In the Irminger Sea&amp;rsquo;s western boundary current system, there are three potential pathways for high-oxygen waters into the deep ocean: (1) The boundary current may be ventilated directly to depths greater than 500m via down-front wind forcing; (2) Labrador Sea Water (LSW), which forms via deep convection in the Labrador and Irminger Basin interiors, drains into the boundary current; (3) Overflow waters spill over the Denmark Strait into the Irminger Sea, entraining LSW and other high-oxygen water masses along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using novel moored O2 measurements in the western Irminger Sea, we aim to quantify the amount of O2 that enters the boundary current through each pathway and elucidate the dynamics that govern each route. The moored O2 sensors were added to existing Overturning in the North Atlantic Program (OSNAP) moorings in summer 2020 in coordination with other O2 sensor deployments on OSNAP moorings across the Labrador Sea. We plan to examine how water masses evolve around the southern tip of Greenland using this combined dataset, as well as how deep water formation and variability couple with oxygen uptake throughout the subpolar North Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This work is funded by NSF and is being undertaken in close collaboration with the NSF-funded GOHSNAP project, whose PIs are Jaime Palter, Roo Nicholson, Hilary Palevsky, and Dariia Atamanchuk.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arrival of New Great Salinity Anomaly Weakens Convection in the Irminger Sea</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/bilo-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/bilo-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slantwise Convection in the Irminger Sea</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/lebras-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/lebras-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclonic Eddies in the West Greenland Boundary Current System</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/pacini-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/pacini-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observation-based estimates of heat and freshwater exchanges from the subtropical North Atlantic to the Arctic</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/li-2021-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/li-2021-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subpolar North Atlantic western boundary density anomalies and the Meridional Overturning Circulation</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/li-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/li-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-Relevant Ocean Transport Measurements in the Atlantic and Arctic Oceans</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/berx-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/berx-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much Arctic fresh water participates in the subpolar overturning circulation?</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking Oxygen and Carbon Uptake with the Meridional Overturning Circulation Using a Transport Mooring Array</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/atamanchuk-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/atamanchuk-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mean Conditions and Seasonality of the West Greenland Boundary Current System near Cape Farewell</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/pacini-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/pacini-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SNAP-DRAGON</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-snap-dragon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-snap-dragon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subpolar North Atlantic Ocean occupies a key role in regional and global climate, yet is poorly
represented in climate models, which limits our confidence in predictions. Recent Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.o-snap.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(OSNAP)&lt;/a&gt; and other
data reveal significant subpolar ocean variability, but raise questions about the processes that give
rise to this variability and that link it to atmospheric changes. We bring the observations together
with numerical ocean and climate models to make a step change in our understanding of subpolar
North Atlantic variability by exposing the time-dependent causal relationships governing
subpolar ocean variability, their robustness across models and their implications for
predictability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This project is a UK-US collaboration led by Helen Johnson (Oxford) together with Penny Holliday (NOC Southampton) and many co-PIs and collaborators. UK funding is provided by the National Environmental Research Council (NERC) and US funding by the National Science Foundation (NSF).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beaufort Gyre Observing System</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-beaufort-gyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-beaufort-gyre/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AMOC connectivity</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-nasa-amoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-nasa-amoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) stabilizes the earth’s climate by redistributing heat, salt, oxygen, and carbon globally. The AMOC, in turn, is thought to be sensitive to changes in climate [IPCC 2014]. However, the link between the AMOC and climate hinges on the assumption of meridional coherence, i.e. that the overturning circulation transports climate anomalies thousands of kilometers across the Atlantic basin. Though meridional coherence has been reported in ocean models, observations of the AMOC are too limited to test the role of the overturning circulation in the climate system on interannual time scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To investigate AMOC connectivity from observations, we will compile a novel dataset at 37N. We plan to construct a decade-long (2004-2014), cross-basin dataset by combining complementary data types: satellite altimetry, gravity and wind stress data, in situ float observations, and the Line W western boundary moored array [Willis and Fu 2008, Toole et al. 2017]. The ECCO v4 and LLC270 state estimates will be used to complement our analysis and test our methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objectives are to use the 37N dataset to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;clarify the effect of subpolar density anomalies on the subtropical AMOC,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;diagnose the gyre and overturning circulation contributions to subtropical heat divergence, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;investigate basin-wide AMOC coherence on interannual time scales during the satellite-era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this work will clarify the role of the AMOC in the climate system. The 37N dataset will be particularly well suited to address these questions because the western boundary currents and deep ocean are directly measured, improving upon a satellite- and float-based AMOC dataset at 41N [Willis 2010].  The Willis [2010] 41N AMOC estimate does not include any observations below 2000m, has limited spatial and temporal resolution, and is situated just north of the subtropical gyre, which limits the scope of scientific questions it can be used to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 37N dataset would provide the oceanographic community with a full-depth AMOC dataset that complements existing cross-basin arrays: OSNAP (Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program) at 57N, and  RAPID (Rapid Climate Change) at  26.5N. This project will expand our understanding of the basin-wide character of the overturning circulation and its associated heat transport, as well as ground truth ocean models. Our methods for merging satellite and in situ observations may be applicable to other ocean regions, which would substantially increase the scope of the global overturning circulation observing system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funded by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Research Opportunities in Space and Earth Sciences (ROSES) Physical Oceanography program.
Co-PI: Joshua Willis (JPL). Additional collaborators: Felix Landerer (JPL), Ian Fenty (JPL), and John Toole (WHOI).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen cycling in the Irminger Sea</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-o2-irminger/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/project/2020-o2-irminger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The high latitude North Atlantic has an outsized impact on global climate as it is one of the few regions where deep and intermediate water masses are formed. These water formation sites are the windows through which gases such as carbon dioxide and oxygen are transferred from the atmosphere to the ocean interior. While traditionally the Labrador Sea has been considered the primary location for convective mixing and gas uptake in the subpolar North Atlantic, in recent years deep convection has also occurred in the Irminger Sea, and observations have shown that processes in the Irminger Sea play a significant role in meridional overturning circulation variability. The variability in carbon dioxide and oxygen uptake in the region is likely also significant, yet has not been characterized to the extent that heat and freshwater fluxes have. The goal of work proposed here is to use observations from the Ocean Observatories Initiative Irminger Sea Global Node together with shipboard and profiling float observations to obtain a basin-wide view of oxygen cycling on seasonal to interannual time scales. We focus on oxygen as it is by far the most sampled biogeochemical variable in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This project is an interdisciplinary collaboration between Isabela Le Bras, Roo Nicholson (WHOI), Hilary Palevsky (BC) and Leah McRaven (WHOI). Funding provided by WHOI Internal Burke OOI Innovation Fund.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Export of Waters Formed by Convection Near the Irminger Sea&#39;s Western Boundary</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation: Observed Transport and Variability</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/frajka-williams-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/frajka-williams-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transport variability of the Irminger Sea Deep Western Boundary Current from a mooring array</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/hopkins-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/hopkins-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A sea change in our view of overturning in the subpolar North Atlantic.</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/lozier-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/lozier-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A barotropic vorticity budget for the subtropical north atlantic based on observations</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/bras-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/bras-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A barotropic vorticity budget for the subtropical north atlantic based on observations</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonality of Freshwater in the East Greenland Current System From 2014 to 2016</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2018-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2018-b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Freshwater Flux from the Greenland Ice Sheet Workshop Report</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/sutherland-2018-x/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/sutherland-2018-x/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Interaction of Recirculation Gyres and a Deep Boundary Current</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moored observations of the Deep Western Boundary Current in the NWAtlantic: 2004-2014</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/toole-2017-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/toole-2017-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of North Atlantic Western Boundary Currents</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking Labrador Sea Water property signals along the Deep Western Boundary Current</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2017-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/le-bras-2017-b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transport of charged particles by adjusting rf voltage amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/karin-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ilebras.github.io/publication/karin-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
